Finding Aid for the Avery Leiserson Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Avery Leiserson Papers
1936-2004
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0256
3.34 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Avery Leiserson was born in 1913 and died February 14, 2004 at the age of 90. He was a native of Madison, Wisconsin. He graduated from the University of Illinois in 1934 with a B.A. degree and in 1941 from the University of Chicago with a Ph.D in Political Science. Early in his career and before the second World War he taught briefly at Princeton University. Then from 1946 until he came to Vanderbilt University in 1952, he taught at the University of Chicago. He was at Vanderbilt until his retirement as Professor Emeritus in 1978. He was a nationally known scholar of American politics who was instrumental in building Vanderbilt’s Political Science department to a position of national prominence.
Professor Leiserson’s great mentor and influence was Charles E. Merriam. In an introduction to a program in 1975 of the American Political Science Asssociation of which Professor Leiserson was president at the time, Samuel Patterson introduced Avery Leiserson as one of the most important leaders in the field of Political Science and noted especially his seminal work “Problems of Methodology in Political Research.” Avery Leiserson is known in addition to his work on methodology in political science “for his concern about values, his devotion to scientific inquiry, and his emphasis on realism all of which were guided by his sense of the value of democracy.”
In the 1960’s Professor Leiserson was active in Civil Rights work, and he was one of a group of Vanderbilt professors who first proposed a Black Studies Program in the College of Arts and Science, which later became the African American Studies Program.
Professor Leiserson was honored with the Harvie Branscomb Distinquished Service Award in 1967 and with an “Avery Leiserson Day” on November 1, 2003 to recognize his many accomplishments during his long life and career.
His published books include:
Administrative Regulation: A Study of Representation of Interests (1942)
Parties and Politics: An Institutional and Behavioral Approach (1958)
The American South in the 1960’s (1964)
With these contributions to others:
Perspectives on the South: Agenda for Research (1967)
Political Research and Political Theory (1968)
Leiserson served as editor of the Journal of Politics and as book review editor of The American Political Science Review.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is 3.34 linear feet, 8 Hollinger boxes which consist of correspondence, articles and book reviews by Avery Leiserson as well as materials relating to his academic career at the University of Chicago (1946 -1952) and at Vanderbilt University (1952 -1978). Other series in this collection include reprints, book reviews, magazine and newspaper articles written by others. The materials cover the years 1936 until his death in 2004.
- Correspondence - Outgoing
  - Dec. 8, 1953 to Dean Ewing P. Shahan (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Feb. 19, 1969 to Prof. W.S. Livingston (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - July 14, 1970 to Harrry H. Ransom (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - Bhambhri, C. P. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biemiller, Andrew J. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bryant, Mavis (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edwards, Richard A. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Henning, John F. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Livingston, William S. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lynch, G. A. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Naqqi, S.A.H. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Parthemos, George S. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Truman, David (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ulmer, S. Sidney (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Weiner, Myron (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ?, Ruth, letter dated May 19, 2001 with photos (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Academic Career – University of Chicago
  - War Assets Administration materials, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Statement of Academic Freedom, Oct. 1949; Special Alumni courses, 1951 -1952 with accompanying bibliography (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Academic Career – Vanderbilt University
  - Poltical Science 251 “The Arrow General Impossibility Theorem” (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Political Science 336 ( Mr. Dorsey) “ Comparative Study of Public Administation” Spring 1970 – Course description (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Political Science 304 (Leiserson ) – assigned reading for Political Theories of Organization – Waldo, Dwight “Developments in Public Administration” (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Department of Political Science, Graduate program reading list, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Political Science Course information (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Program – Southern Political Science Association, Nov. 7 – 9, 1968; Program – Fifty-seventh Annual meeting – Southern Political Science Association, Nov. 7 – 9, 1985, signed by Manning Dauer. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - V.O. Key, Jr. – A.Leiserson’s research notes, 1958; Bibliography, 1931 – 1964; “Old V.O.” Student – Faculty Colloquium at Vanderbilt. Jan. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report of the Atomic Energy Labor Relations Panel, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Legal document of petition Faculty appointments, filed April 6, 1951 in the District Court of Appeal of the State of California (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - University of Delhi, Department of Sociology, Annual Report, 1965 – 66; 1966 – 67; Syllabus for the M.A. Examination in Sociology and University of Delhi, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Panel Discussion American Political Science Association, Sept. 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, Delhi, 1995 -96; Obituary of Prof. B. Ahmed, Sept. 14, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Political Science Association Memorandum on support for Political Science program, 1973; Social Science Research Council – Fellowships and Grants for Training and Research to be offered in 1986 -87; Citizens’ Research Foundation Brochure (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Education Budget and Bills (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Papers for research (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Research notes (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Research notes (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Research notes (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Academic Career – Vanderbilt University – Photographs
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952, # 427 - 447 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 448 - 457 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 464 - 473 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 474 - 486 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 487 - 496 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 497 - 513 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 514 - 523 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Building of Memorial Gymnasium on the Vanderbilt Campus, 1952 # 524 - 540 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Writings by Avery Leiserson – Articles and reprints
  - “Political Limitations on Executive Reorganization,” in American (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Political Science Review, Vol. 41, Feb.1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - “Organized Labor as a Pressure Group” (pp. 108 – 117) in Labor in the (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Economy, The Annals, Vol. 274, March 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “ Organized Labor as a Pressure Group” reprinted from The Annals of the (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Academy of Political and and Social Science, Philadelphia, March 1951 with accompanying research notes (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - “The Place of Parties in the Study of Politics” reprinted from The American (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Political Science Review, Vol. 61, No. 4, December 1957 with accompanying Abstract (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - “Science and the Public Life” Address at the Southern Political Science Association, November 11, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - “India’s Political Culture and the State of its Political Science” November 1968, typescript (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “India’s Political Culture and the State of its Political Science” November 1968, multiple copies of the typescript (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - “Charles Merriam, Max Weber, and the Search for Synthesis in Political (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Science” reprinted from The American Political Science Review, Vol. LXIX, No. 1, March 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - “On Defining Politics and How to Take It into Account”, June 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Writings by Avery Leiserson – Reviews
  - Review of American Labor from Defense to Reconversion by Joel Seidman in Journal of Politics, May 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Review of Regulating Business by Independent Commission by Marver H. Bernstein, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Review of The Development of the Social Security Act by Edwin E.Witte, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Review of “The Politics of Science: Science Politics, Science Policy, Policy Science – The Whole Thing” in Polity, Vol. VI, No. 1 / Fall 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Review of Max Weber and the Theory of Modern Politics by David Beetham, in American Political Science Review, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reviews of Avery Leiserson’s book Parties and Politics: An Institutional and Behavioral Approach, 1958 by Ralph K. Huitt in Political Science Quarterly, 1959 and by Austin Ranney in Midwest Journal of Political Science Feb. 1959 and James C. Davies in American Political Science Review, Sept. 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Writings by others – articles and reprints
  - Adler, Kenneth P. and Bobrow, Davis “Interest and Influence in Foreign (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Affairs” reprinted from The Public Opinion Quarterly, Vol. XX, No. 1, Spring 1956 with attached letter dated, April 25, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ahmed, Aqueil “Science as a Management Problem” in Economic and Political Weekly, Aug. 3, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ahmed, Aqueil “Progress in the Science of Science with Special Reference to India” Center for the Study of Social and Cultural Change, University of North Dakota, May 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Almond, Gabriel A. “Psychology, Numbers, and Political Science: Merriam’s Prophecy Fulflled and Unfulfilled” an address at the annual meeting of the American Political Science Association, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Anderson, Charles W. “ The Political Economy of Charles E. Lindblom” an essay in The American Political Science Review, Vol. 72 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ashmore, Harry S. “The Strange Case of Kim Dae-Jung” a dialogue discussion paper presented in Seoul, South Korea, May 21, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bass, Harold F., Jr. “Change and Democratization in One-Party Systems” in The Midsouth Political Science Journal, Vol. 12, Autumn, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Baumann, Fred “The University and the State: the Proper Role of Government in Higher Education” in Measure, No. 41, Feb. 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bawa, Vasant Kumar “Changing Indian Attitudes Towards the Developing Political and Economic Situation in Asia” address given to Nashville Committee on Foreign Relations, Sept. 29, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Birkby, Robert H. “Politics of Accommodation: The Origin of the Supremacy Clause” reprinted from the Western Political Quarterly, March, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Boorman, Howard L. “Western Biographies and Chinese Realities” a paper given at the American Historical Association meeting in New York, December 30, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Boorman, Howard L. and Scott A. Boorman “Strategy and National Psychology in China” reprinted from the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Philadelphia, Vol. 370, March 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Boulware, L.R. “ Politics …The Businessman’s Biggest Job in 1958” address before the Annual Meeting of the Phoenix Chamber of Commerce, May 21, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Brodie, Bernard “Some Strategic Implications of the Nuclear Revolution,” Institute of International Studies, University of Utah (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Campbell, Angus; Gurin, Gerald, Miller, Warren E. “ Television’s Campaign (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Audiences” Survey Research Center, University of Michigan, March 10, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chandidas, R. “The Fourth General Elections Madhya Pradesh: A Case Study” reprinted from Economic and Political Weekly, Special Number, August 1967 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cole, Kenneth C. “The Theory of Democracy in the West: What Kind of Democracy Shall We Profess?” reproduced from the Proceedings of the Institute of World Affairs, Vol. XXXII, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Cook, Thomas I “The Political System: The Stubborn Search for a Science of Politics” reprinted from the Journal of Philosophy, March 1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cornelius, William G. “The County Unit System of Georgia: Facts and Prospects” reprinted from The Western Political Quarterly, December 1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Cosman, Bernard “ An Overview of Southern Republicanism” prepared for delivery at the 1964 Southern Political Science Association in Durham, North Carolina, Nov.12 - 14, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Cox, Edward F. “ The Measurement of Party Strength” reprinted from The Western Political Quarterly, Vol. XIII, No. 4, December 1960 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Writings by others – articles and reprints
  - Dahl, Robert A. “ The Concept of Power” reprint, April 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Daru, C.T. “Appeal for Public Debate: A Fresh Look at Our Constitution”, Dec. 9, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - David, Paul T. “The Changing Party Pattern” Reprint No. 15 The Brookings Institution, September 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - David, Paul T. “Experimental Approaches to Vote-Counting Theory in Nominating Choice” reprinted from The American Political Science Review, Vol. LVI, No. 3, September 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dragnich, Alex N. “Recent Political Developments in Yugoslavia” in The Journal of Politics, vol. 20, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dragnich, Alex N. “ Bewilderment Among the Serbs” in Serbian Studies, Journal of the North American Society for Serbian Studies, Vol. 13, No. 1, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dragnich, Alex N. Review of To End A War by Richard Holbrooke 1998 Accompanying letter, Sept. 7, 1999 with two letters to the editors (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Drew, David E. “Reorganizing Washington: Policy Research and Social Scientists” in the National Observer’s Sounding Board of Opinion, May 16, 1977 with cover letter David Drew to Glen Clanton, June 6, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Eby, Kermit “Labor’s Emerging Role in the Political Economy” for the Conference on Science, Philosophy, and Religion (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fox, William T. R. “Collective Enforcement of Peace and Security” reprinted from The American Political Science Review, Vol. XXXIX, No. 5, Oct. 1945; “The Super-Powers at San Francisco” reprinted from The Review of Politics, Vol. 8, No.1, January 1946; “Frederick Sherwood Dunn and the American Study of International Relations” in World Politics, Vol. XV, No. 1, October 1962;”The Demand for Freedom” reprinted from The American Society of International Law, April 1981; “E.H. Carr and Political Realism: Vision and Revision” in Review of International Studies, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Freeman, J. Leiper “Tennessee Political Change” presented at the Citadel Symposium on Southern Politics, Charleston, South Carolina, Feb. 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Freeman, J. Leiper “Parents, It’s Not All Your Fault, But …” in The Journal Politics, Vol. 31, 1969; “Testimony to the McGovern Commission”, Aug. 11, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Frohock, Fred M. “Individuals and Aggregates: the Generalization Argument Reconsidered” in Social Theory and Practice, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gaillard, Frye “Indians in Revolt - 1970” Race Relations Information Center Nashville, Tennessee, December 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Goldman, Ralph M. - Summary of a Dissertation “Party Chairmen and Party Faction, 1789 - 1900: A Theory of Executive Responsibility and Conflict Resolution”, June 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Grady, Robert C., II “Property and Natural Political Virtue: the Implications of Locke as a Liberal” reprinted from Polity, Vol. X, No. 1, Fall 1977 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Gunnell, John G. “American Political Science, Liberalism, and the Invention of Political Theory” in American Political Science Review, Vol. 82, No. 1, March 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Graham, George J., Jr. “Edmund Burke’s Developmental Consensus” reprinted from Midwest Journal of Political Science, Vol. XVI, No. 1, Feb. 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Graham, George J., Jr. “Wealth of Nations, Federalist #10, and Value Validity” paper prepared for the Bicentennial Conference on Adam Smith and the Wealth of Nations, 1776 - 1976, Richmond, Kentucky, March 25, 1976; “Technology in Political Philosophy and Theory: Conceptual Analysis and Normative and Empirical Consequences” presented at the XIIth World Congress of the International Political Science Association, Rio de Janeiro, August 9 – 14, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hancock, M. Donald “Comparative Public Policy: An Assessment” prepared for delivery at the annual meeting of the American Political Science Association in Denver, Colorado, September 2 – 5, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hardin, Charles M. “A Political Interpretation of Agricultural Issues” an address at the Graduate School of the U.S. Department of Agriculture on December 8, 1954; “To Make Our Case – and Expand our Base,”, August, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Heard, Alexander “A University and Its Community” remarks made in a talk before the Rotary Club of Nashville, February 25, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Heberle, Rudolf and Bertrand, Alvin L. “Factors Motivating Voting Behavior in a One Party State: A Case Study of the 1948 Louisiana Gubernatorial Primaries” reprinted from Social Forces, Vol. 27, No. 4, May 1949; Herring Pendleton “On the Study of Government” reprinted from The American Political Science Review, Vol. XLVII, No. 4, December, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hirsch, Michael “At War with Ourselves: In Kosovo, America Confronts its own Ideals” in Harper’s Magazine, Vol. 299, No.1790, July 1999 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Holland, Thomas “The Labor Management Conferences” Report, 1950; Hutchins, Robert M. “Academic Freedom” remarks before the American Academy of Political and Social Science, Philadelphia, PA, April 2, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Kim, Young C. “The Functions of Political Orientations: A Typology” and Gordon, Bernard K. “Problems of Regional Cooperation in Southeast Asia” in World Politics, Vol. XVI, No. 2, January 1964 with attached note from Young C. Kim, Feb. 15, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Kirkpatrick, Evron M. “Toward a More Responsible Two-Party System: Political Science, Policy Science, or Pseudo – Science?” prepared for delivery at the sixty-sixth Annual Meeting of the American Political Science Association, Los Angeles, CA, Sept. 8 - 12, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Kothari, Rajni “India’s Political Transition” reprinted from Economic Political Weekly, Special Number, August 1967; “Democracy in Decay: the Decline and Fall of the American Empire” in Sunday World, New Delhi, Vol. 11, No. 4, January 23, 1972; “The Congress System Revisited: A Decennial Review” reprinted from December, 1974, issue of Asian Survey; “End of an Era”; Profile of Rajni Kothari by Elizabeth J. Hollins as part of World Order Models Project, Winter 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Kothari, Rajni “Changing Nature of Human Conflict in Our Times” and “Choices Facing a Divided World” Dyason Memorial Lectures, 1974, Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, Delhi, India (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Writings by others – articles and reprints
  - Kothari, Rajni “Implications of Nation-Building for the Typology of Political Systems” address before the International Political Science Association Seventh World Congress, September 18 – 23, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Kothari, Rajni “Nation – Making and Concensus: The Case of the Indian National Congress” presented at the International Political Science Association, Brussels, September 1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Kothari, Rajni “Processes of Political Modernisation” discussion paper for Specialist Meeting on Processes of Political Modernisation, Brussels, September 18 - 23, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Kothari, Rajni “Political Economy of Development” R.R. Kale Memorial Lecture, 1971; “Political Economy of Garibi Hatao” reprinted from Economic and Political Weekly, Vol. VII, Nos. 31 - 33, Special Number, August 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Kothari, Rajni “ The Political Economy of Employment” prepared for the Seminar on the Employment Process, Bogota, February 21 - 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ladd, Everett Carll, Jr. “Liberalism Upside Down” in the Political Science Quarterly, Vol. 91, No. 4, Winter 1976 -77 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Land, Edwin Herbert “Addiction as a Necessity and Opportunity” reprint (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lane, Robert E. “The Politics of Consensus in an Age of Affluence” reprinted from The American Political Science Review, Vol. LIX, No. 4, December, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Landau, Martin “ The Classroom and Political Science, or, Teaching is Not a Political Act” preliminary draft of paper for Iowa Conference, October 1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Leiserson, Michael “Economic Interests and Foreign Policy: The Case of Britain and the European Movement” a senior thesis submitted to the Department of Politics, Princeton University, April 19, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Leiserson, William “Industrial Fluctuations and Unemployment” address delivered at forty-third annual meeting of the American Economic Association, Cleveland, Ohio, December 30, 1930; Right and Wrong in Labor Relations, the Barbara Weinstock Lecture on the Morals of Trade Delivered at the University of California, April 8, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - . Leiserson, William M. “Growing Pains of the American Labor Movement” in Labor Relations and the War, Vo1. 224, November, 1942 in The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Leiserson, William “Public Policy in Labor Relations” reprinted from American Economic Review Proceedings, Vol. XXXVI, No. 2, May, 1946; “The Role of Government in Industrial Relations” address delivered at the Industrial Relations Institute, University of California, March 20, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - “The Function of Mediation in Labor Relations” address before the 4th annual meeting of the Industrial Relations Research Association, Boston, Mass., December 29, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - McClosky, Herbert “Consensus and Ideology in American Politics” reprinted from The American Political Science Review, Vol. LVIII, No. 2, June 1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - McClosky, Herbert and Schaar, John H. “Psychological Dimensions of Anomy” reprinted from American Sociological Review, Vol. 30, No. 1, February, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Mandelbaum, Michael “ A Perfect Failure: Nato’s War Against Yugoslavia” in Foreign Affairs, Vol. 78, No. 5, September/October 1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mansfield, Harvey C. “Federal Executive Reorganization: Thirty Years of Experience” reprinted from Public Administration Review, Vol. 29, No. 4, July/August 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - March, R. R. and Jackson, R. J. “ Aspects of the State of Political Science in Canada” reprinted from Midwest Journal of Political Science, Vol. XI, No. 4, Nov. 1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Writings by others – articles and reprints
  - Maru, Rushikesh “Research Development in India and China: A Comparative Analysis of Research Statistics and Research Effort” preliminary draft of an occasional paper No. 1, Lund, Sweden, April 10, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Meany, George “Political Education is an A.F. of L. Tradition” reprinted from the American Federationist, September 1953 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Merriam, Charles E. “ Democracy: An Alumni School Address” reprinted from the University of Chicago Magazine, June 1940 (Box 5, Folder 2)